Miguel Sabogal García

Curriculum Vitæ

Mail: msabogal@est.uniatlantico.edu.co Contact page: msabogal.github.io Telephone: + 57 3017958948

Over the last 3 years I actively participated in many physics research that resulted in international scientific publications. These experiences allowed me to acquire strengths in leadership, creativity and perseverance, while building skills in a wide range of programming languages, developing specialized software and performing data management through process automation.

Professional experience

05/2022 - 08/2022 Research intern, RECA Internship program 2022, Red de Estudiantes de Astronomía de Colombia.

Tasks performed:

- Design and development of specialized software in Python
- Statistical analysis using Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC)
- Writing of scientific articles
- Non-parametric reconstruction using Gaussian Processes (Machine Learning)
- Keep the project manager informed of the overall status of the solution
- Develop the end to end project plans with the execution team
- Be part of technical discussions and solution

05/2022 - 06/2022 **Supportive Mentor**, Pgm. de Apoyo a la Permanencia y Graduación estudiantil, Universidad del Atlántico Tasks performed:

- In-person and virtual classes of Physics and Mathematics
- Academic support to students in their first semesters and mid-career.
- Mentoring colleagues providing advice and guidance on best practice and development techniques

Education

• 2015 – 2022 **Physicist,** Bachelor's degree/ Universidad del Atlántico.

Computational skills

Python: Advanced, C/C++: Intermediate, Fortran 90: Intermediate, MATLAB/Mathematica/Excel: Advanced, HTML: Basic

Techniques: Process Automation, Gaussian Processes (Machine Learning), Statistical analysis using MCMC, Web scraping, Object-oriented programming.

Tools: Selenium, Beautifulsoup, Scrapy, Numpy, SciPy, Pandas.

Research Experience, Publications and Projects

Peer-Reviewed Publications

- Oliveros, A., **Sabogal, M.A.,** & Acero, M.A. Barrow holographic dark energy with Granda–Oliveros cutoff. Eur. Phys. J. Plus 137, 783 (2022). DOI: 10.1140/epip/s13360-022-02994-z
- Sabogal, M. A., Parra, I. C., Bandera, M., Gallardo, J., & Mejía-Cortés, C. (2020, May). Mobility of localized beams in non-homogeneous photonic lattices. In Journal of Physics: Conference Series (Vol. 1547, No. 1, p. 012023). IOP Publishing. DOI: 10.1088/1742-6596/1547/1/012023

Manuscripts Under Review

• Cardona, W., & **Sabogal, M.A.** (2022). Holographic energy density, dark energy sound speed, and tensions in cosmological parameters: H0 and S8. arXiv preprint <u>arXiv:2210.13335</u>.

In Preparation

• **Sabogal, M.A.**, & Gonzalez, J.(2022). Hubble constant estimation from BAO signals with LSST-simulated data. <u>Draft:</u> zenodo.7131390

Honors and Awards

- Funding award "Enabling Science Program 2021 Award 51", granted by the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) observatory.
- Undergraduate Honors Theses, Universidad del Atlántico.

Additional languages

English (TOEFL) Read: C1 Speak: B2 Write: B2 Listen: C1 Test date: Nov 2022

Presentations and Events

Event: XIV Latin American Symposium on High Energy Physics

Type of event: International Congress

Type of participation: Speaker

Conference title: Decoding Holographic Dark Energy in the structure formation.

Place: QUITO, ECUADOR - Universidad San Francisco de Quito, 14/11/2022 - 18/11/2022.

Courses and certifications

SAFETY AND HEALTH AT WORK Course (2022) **PYTHON IN ASTRONOMY** Course (2022)

Work references

Mario A. Acero Ortega, PhD in Physics.

Associate Professor

Physics Program, Faculty of Basic Sciences, Universidad del Atlántico.

(+57) 313 497-3415

Javier E. Gonzalez Sanchez, PhD in Astronomy.

Associate professor and supervisor in the *Red de Estudiantes de Astronomía de Colombia*. Universidade Federal de Sergipe, Brazil. javiergonzalezs@academico.ufs.br

Personal references

Jorge L. Navarro Estrada, PhD in Physics.

Associate Professor Physics Program, School of Basic Sciences, Universidad del Atlántico. (+57) 301 707-8117